Okay, this presentation is going to be in English, but first I'm gonna say hello to everyone in Greek Hera Kapalua
Yeah oldest with an assumed era in a after poll in a monopolist Nokia all balloon the Punto no mama
Omona de bourree. Say Oh Lisa's honest police ant openers Anto police Anto Poulos
Tonic a typhoon a esto para su bono born puno little Omaha born on a cake on asados a de la Pelosi
Lodi the Nick Spano anima
Cytosolic Satoshi nakamoto's
nee her suburban LaGuerta Ted the broad for a pagar para seasonal Ovid Olivia's Katrina
so hackerspace
eaten a
Octo-octo-octopus
the directory for a began operations in a lava
Stone scenario des disrupt la ribera portico she of tapasya between the necks reckon Ana's
The dread for upon Aparicio sustain a la vez de officia
eaten a
pura basura de
anthropic torah
trakis penida
Kalapa me
So thank you all for coming. We'll do the rest of the presentation in English
Partly because we have an international audience
Ready to get started is everybody excited to be here?
This is the biggest the biggest meet-up of the local Bitcoin blockchain community in Athens. And
My job my favorite job is to build community
so
Please connect with your local community and find ways to come to more of these meetings
So that you can engage with other people in communities when I go around the world
and I talk about
Open block chains and crypto currencies people often have different motivations. They ask me different questions
about this technology
right now in
Greece a lot of the interests is
about how to find ways to invest
Okay. So how many people are interested in investment?
Great, and how many people are interested in technology?
You're lying
Okay, so and people ask me often
What should I invest in and I don't do investment advice. I'm a technologist but tonight
What we're gonna do is we're going to talk about that. So
Tonight's talk is about the next Bitcoin, which is a question
I get all the time which is what is going to be the next Bitcoin, right?
Sometimes I get asked what is going to be the next aetherium
and
So that's what I want to talk about tonight and in order to help you
I'm going to start by telling you the answer at the beginning as a
spoiler so the next Bitcoin
which you might consider investing in is going to be
Bitcoin
But here's why and and this is important to understand a lot of people are looking for an
opportunity to invest in something that did what bitcoin did since 2009
They're looking for an opportunity to find
The next thing that's going to be super successful
That's going to maybe do
10x or 100x in its price not going to happen and
The reason it's not going to happen is because Bitcoin was created and born in very very unique
Circumstances, so what are those?
circumstances
some people call this bitcoins virgin birth the Immaculate Conception
right
Which I'm sure is blasphemy, especially in Greece, but that's okay. So
what do we mean by the
Virgin birth of Bitcoin. You got to realize that back in 2009 when Bitcoin was launched and
If you went to anyone and you said hey
how about
Instead of government's doing money. The internet does money and everybody were like
Yeah, that's that's never gonna work. That's no that's that can't work. No
And then if you explain nobody it's a really interesting
algorithm
For most people when they hear the word algorithm, they automatically switch off right unless they're computer scientists
You say algorithm there. Like there must be someone else at this party I could talk to
Because this person just said algorithm so
Like we're not there if you say it was very interesting
like it's a decentralized system that allows you to create a monetary supply of deflationary assets that
distributed an affaire methods through proof of work consensus and
Then at that point there really like there must be someone else at this party I can talk to
So you got to realize in 2009. Nobody believed any of this shit could actually work
Which is why it did
Because if you believe it works
What are you gonna do if you actually believe this thing is gonna do 10x or 100x
It's gonna increase in value 100 times. What are you gonna do?
You're gonna sell everything you have and buy this thing and then when it becomes a hundred times bigger
You're rich you go home you retire. I don't know right you go to better parties and
if
You know that
Then everybody does it and if everybody does it then it doesn't happen
Right one of the most guaranteed ways
You know that this technology is in the bubble is when people you haven't seen since high school
Call you up like me and like hey Andreas remember me?
Remember me
Is this a good time to buy Bitcoin? I heard that the price drop. Yeah. Is this a good time?
No, if you're calling me for the first time in 28 years to ask me. This is a clear indication
To sell probably like at this point
I'm beginning to think I should sell because if it's beginning to attract your kind of people who had no interest
You know the same people who called me crazy two years ago. Now's the time to get out
This is what happens with markets. If too many people think that it's a sure bet
You're dealing with suckers
right and as they say in poker if you can't tell within 30 minutes who the idiot at the poker table is
You're the idiot, right?
So if you're like no, this is a sure thing I've told all my friends about it
Everybody believes me. You're like, okay now is the time to get out. I
really advise people again and again and again
Invest in understanding the technology invest in skills invest in education invest in knowledge because knowledge
Doesn't lose 40% of its value in a weekend
Knowledge doesn't crash
Knowledge doesn't get hacked by the latest group of hackers
Knowledge doesn't get banned by the government or whatever announcement knowledge is not tweeted about by
President Donald Trump as happened today
Bitcoin got tweeted about by President Donald Trump today
Yeah
He said it had no value and is probably used by criminals, I'm sure he asked some of his friends
So the bottom line is
knowledge and education is an investment you can make that will last and
Even if Bitcoin fails the knowledge and education you get from Bitcoin doesn't go away, right?
But anytime I tell people that they're like yeah, yeah, okay
But what should I buy?
No, you should educate yourself. Yeah. Yeah, but what should I buy?
And that's the problem right? Because if you have an indication of something you should buy you shouldn't
Really go buying that. Okay, and if you need to ask someone else
What you should buy that means you don't understand the technology well enough to make that decision on your own
Are you confident enough to say I think this technology has some unique
differentiation good market fit the timing is right the
Momentum of the market the liquidity is there like if you understand all of that then okay
You're qualified to make that decision on your own and if you're not qualified to make that decision on your own you really shouldn't be
Investing in this thing, right?
So is it an investment or not? And what is
the next Bitcoin and
that's the fundamental problem because there is no next Bitcoin Bitcoin was able to achieve what it achieved because
Nobody for three or four years
Believed that this thing could work
That's why it did what it did
When you see someone
investing in a technology
that every single person around them think is
insane and
Then they make a hundred times a return on their investments
The reason they made a hundred times return on investment is because everything everyone around them thought they were insane
They were taking an enormous risk
right
I'll tell you about the first time I
bought Bitcoin
okay, so I have known about Bitcoin for almost a year and
I was reading all of these scientific papers and I was trying to understand how it worked and
It was very interesting to me as a computer scientist
I was very interested in the technology, but I also wanted to try to use it
so in order to try to use it, I needed to buy a
Tiny amount of Bitcoin. So I am my comfort at that point was I need to buy like a
hundred dollars worth of Bitcoin so in
2012 I decided I'm gonna buy a hundred dollars worth of Bitcoin now in order to do that
I had to go to a grocery store
To use a service called MoneyGram
where you stand in front of a red telephone in America and you call someone so they can
Charge your credit card
To transfer money and this is used mostly by poor people who don't have a bank account in order to pay their bills
so you put in the machine or you give cash to the person at the grocery store and
Once they verify that they send that cash so you can pay your electricity bill or your telephone bill
It's used by people who don't have bank accounts. I use that service
to send a hundred dollars to
An exchange in Japan which was the only exchange that existed for Bitcoin at the time
Called mt.gox and if you know anything about mt.gox, you know, all of the horrible things that happened after
But they didn't happen to me at the time because I actually managed to buy some Bitcoin that way
Every single person in my life said that I was crazy
Not only that I was crazy but that I had lost all of my money which I was ok with. All right, so hundred dollars
Now people today
Want the same answer they want to find out what can I invest in today?
where I can put in a hundred dollars and it's the next Bitcoin and it does one of these things and
the simple answer is that that doesn't exist and
the reason it doesn't exist because the whole world is looking for that and when they're looking for that what happens is
people with a lot more experience
In markets and a lot more money than you are now interested. So if they see something that they think
could work
But what do I mean by work? I?
Don't mean they think this is the technology that could replace Bitcoin
What I mean is they think that you will think that this is the technology that could replace Bitcoin. They're like Oh,
lots of people who know nothing at about
Investments will think this is the one it's got slick marketing. It's got some people on the webpage
It's got some fancy words like quantum AI drones
autonomous and
People who know nothing about this market the people who are looking for the next
Bitcoin are going to believe the is the next Bitcoin
So what they do is they get into the market with a lot of money when the price is really early on
Then they wait for all of you to go. I'll just put in a hundred euro, where what's wrong worst case
I lose my hundred euro
Yeah, that's exactly what's gonna happen. And that system of investment is called pump and dump
Right, so what they do is they put our money into this investment then they go out on social media and they buy
people to go and say this is the next thing this is the next thing you go in and say I'll just put in a
Hundred euros just in case, you know, I mean, maybe I could get lucky you're better off playing the lotto
Right, you're better off playing
Propo do they still have that here?
It's like the football sweepstakes and so as soon as lots of people who are not
Informed about these investments go and buy it with their little hundred euro investments
They then do the second part of the plan, which is called dump, right?
so they did the pump now they do the dump and what they do is they sell all of
their shit coin
and then the price crashes but they made a huge return on investment and
All of the people who put in a hundred euros just in case go. Ah, that wasn't the one
but
This next one that's IOT AI
drones
And quantum is going to be the next Bitcoin so then they repeat and so on and so forth
the bottom line is that Bitcoin happens at a moment in history when nobody was expecting this thing to work and
None of the people that were really involved in the early days believed that this was a good investment
they believed it was an interesting technology and
In order to try and use that technology like I did
You had to get some of it to try out
So it kind of accidentally became an investment
and by the way
If you think that story
starts with and then I went to the grocery store and I picked up the red phone and I bought Bitcoin at
$2 and then I became rich
Right, that's not how it works
That's exactly what happens. I bought $100 worth of Bitcoin. Each Bitcoin was two dollars. So I bought like 50
Next week, I bought another 50 right and then you're like, oh, yeah, so
Wow
This is how it actually works
Three months later, it goes from $2 to $8 and I go yeah
score I quadrupled my investment, which means that now if I sell my
$200 I have 800 fucking dollars. I can buy an Xbox
So I sold it all and bought an Xbox
And
This keeps happening. Again that this has happened to everybody who's gotten involved because it's very easy to think
Oh, I would understand immediately that this investment would go to like
Thousands of dollars, but if you told me in 2012, oh, it's two dollars now, but in 2019
it's gonna be thirteen thousand dollars like
Yeah, right
That's never gonna happen. And if I told you today, let's do the same experiment if I told you today in three years
It's gonna be a hundred and fifty thousand dollars. How many of you think yes
Okay
That's unrealistic
That's totally unrealistic. It might happen
Right, but am I not and do you take that kind of risk? Do you take the risk in January to say?
Oh, it's 3000
It's been crashing for two years straight now is a good time to buy everybody thinks they do that
The strategy seems simple on its face
Buy low sell high in
Practice what you end up doing is a somewhat similar strategy called buy high sell low
Where what you do is when everybody gets excited you buy some then it crashed
Then you panic then you sell it to the lowest price and then you keep repeating that. How do I know done it?
Right who hasn't?
Okay, really who hasn't?
Okay, five people very good. So
The bottom line is that we're all looking for this next opportunity
And the reason it's not going to happen is because of the unique circumstances
I
like to think of this a bit by comparing it to
biology, right and if you think about biology and you understand how evolution works and how an
environmental
niche or
Area works if there's a very successful species, right?
And that species finds an environment in which it is very successful
It has the right amount of food. It has no predators, etc, etc
It will dominate that environment like dominated think for example, what happens when?
stupid Europeans introduced rabbits to Australia and
There was nothing that could eat
rabbits rabbits everywhere
Right and then they're like, oh, let's introduce this other species that will leave that species and then the got too many of those
because if you do that in an environment where there's no
anything
fitting in that particular niche, right and
It has no predators and it has plenty of food. What is it gonna do?
It's gonna fuck all day until there's lots of rabbits
right
That's what it's gonna do and then you have a lot a lot of rabbits
I mean, you know, they pop out eight in every generation, which is approximately every six days
So before you know, it talk about exponential growth like Bitcoin has nothing compared to rabbits the bottom line
Is that if you have an environment in which a species become successful it?
Dominates that environments but interestingly enough if you then introduce another species that is similar
But slightly more efficient or more successful, it fails completely
Why?
because that
Environment has already been dominated and simply a sheer numbers
Mean that the new species even if it's more efficient
Cannot propagate in that environment because there's five of it and there's six million rabbits
So even if it manages to be very successful, it doesn't meet very many of its own kinds but it keeps meeting rabbits
All right, and every time there's an opportunity for food a whole bunch of rabbits show up. This is the idea of
Biological evolution if you have an environment in which there is one organism that is very successful it
Dominates that environment and it then closes that environment to everything else that can fit in that environment
So what happened with Bitcoin?
Bitcoin found a very unique application and that was non government money as it can spread globally
That is completely uncensored
decentralized
unstoppable and borderless in a pure digital form
Okay that application in that environment is now taken
So when someone comes and says we can do a slightly better Bitcoin
Great, you can do a slightly better Bitcoin. Nobody will care
Because all of the software developers have not been trained in you're slightly better Bitcoin
Right. So if bitcoin is B, let's call the other one. Let's start it with a C. So it's the next iteration sit coin
so
Let's say you have set coin and it comes along. It's like we're the next Bitcoin and maybe that's true
Maybe it's a bit more scalable or has better security characteristics or is easier to use and it's got a enough
Differentiation that if they both start it out it would win
it would absolutely win if they both start it out at the same time it would win but now it
Starts out in an environment where all of the developers already know how to do Bitcoin
where the book says
mastering Bitcoin
where the software libraries are for Bitcoin where the exchanges have Bitcoin and it has a lot of liquidity where there's
26 different
wallets for it
where you can easily find people at the local Starbucks or
some better coffee shop to trade and
Get some Bitcoin but if you start going well, do you have some shit coin and you're like, well, no
But we do have some Bitcoin but like it's better. Yeah, but I
Don't have any and everybody I know is already interested in this other thing
So
How much does the new thing have to differentiate?
Well, this is the real challenge because if it differentiates enough if it's different enough
From Bitcoin. Well, then it's no longer
occupying the same environmental nish
It's no longer competing against Bitcoin now. It's competing for something else and maybe it becomes dominance in that space and
in order to do that you have to do a lot of hard work because if you want to start a new
Cryptocurrency with its own security you have to bootstrap that
Security in an environment where people are going to attack you on day one on
Day one nobody attacks Bitcoin on day two. Nobody attacks Bitcoin on day
1074 nobody attacks Bitcoin. Nobody had really heard of it. Nobody thought it would work on day
2,500 nobody attacks Bitcoin, right?
It took years before anybody thought this thing would actually work to start attacking it and by that time it
Was strong enough to resist the attack
Now you go out to you're like I have an idea and it's better than Bitcoin everywhere. It goes Brewin
They attack your system and the next morning it's gone
right
Because you get hacked you get crashed
You go out and do proof of work. All right. I've got a new proof of work
I'll ger them and everybody comes in with their GPUs
Why do they have GPUs because they've spent the last five years mining aetherium or whatever right
So they have plenty of GPUs. They're like, oh, could I take a few?
Thousand GPUs and throw it to this new coin and see if I can dominate the network. They sure can
Right. So then they dominate the network there goes your security like okay, we can't do proof of work
Let's do proof of stake proof of stake. It's gonna be much easier
Because then what it really needs in order to someone to attack it is rich people. Oh
shit
There's lots of them and they're all trying to break
crypto now
so you saw a proof of stake and who buys all of the stake rich people and
The only reason rich people didn't buy all of the Bitcoin in the beginning is because they thought it wasn't going to work
But if you try to do it today, they're all looking for the next Bitcoin that they can sell
to you
To the people who don't know any better. I
remember when etherium launched and
I remember receiving the email the Vitalik sent out
to ask for
comments and
this was in December of
2013 and
He sent it out to a bunch of people in the space and he said listen, I've got this new idea
We're looking for developers. We're looking for investors and
I'd like to invite you all to read the white paper
so I went and I read the white paper and I had one question and this question was
Why are you not doing this on Bitcoin?
Why would you go to all of the effort of launching a separate chain?
so I
Called Vitalik on skype and I talked to metallic
in his kitchen and
He patiently explained to me that he had already tried to do it on Bitcoin
He had tried to do it with what's called the master coin protocol on top of Bitcoin and he had very quickly realized that
Bitcoin was too
specific to work for the purpose that aetherium was and
That you couldn't really do the same security model and he said I think this is general enough
Different enough an important enough that it's worth the effort
to bootstrap a
new security chain, it's really really hard to do and
Aetherium was different enough that it did it
Maybe we'll see
Right, maybe it work
It's not yet certain it seems to be doing okay so far sometimes
Sometimes not so well, right
But they managed to bootstrap a new security chain because it was different enough from Bitcoin
but then the interesting thing that happened is now if you talk to people who are really into a theory and they're like
We can do everything
including what Bitcoin does
No, you can't
No, you can because all of the things you did to differentiate enough from Bitcoin. I mean that you're playing in a completely different environment
You're playing for the generalized
Flexible smart contract space and every choice you make for that design means you can't play in the highly specialized
Highly secure robust. We can resist attacks from governments space
For the open free money of the world
application the Bitcoin already fully occupies
Aetherium can be the next Bitcoin
But the funny thing that happens next is while etherion people alike. We could be the next Bitcoin some other people are going. Yeah, but
We could be the next aetherium
And before you know it everyone the theory was looking over their shoulder and going who are you? Where did you come from?
Why are you coming from my application?
It's ok, because they can't be the next to theorem either
For exactly the same reason the application space for a virtual machine-based
general smart contracts application platform is
solidly occupied by aetherium
Not because it's the best
But because it got there first
Survived long enough and did okayish
For long enough to dominate the space and now all of the libraries are for aetherium
All of the application developers are Furth and as a result if you're trying to make your own thing to compete against that
You can find enough attention
so
There isn't a next aetherium because that space is already taken
What does it take for one of these technologies to be replaced?
What does it take for something to replace Bitcoin or to replace aetherium? It doesn't happen because
Someone invented a slightly better solution or even a much better solution that will work
Instead it can only happen if the system that already occupies
this space fully
fails on its own
so in order for something to be the next Bitcoin first Bitcoin has to fail like really
spectacularly fail
Not a bit knocks, like oh we lost two hundred million dollars because someone hacked in exchange again
Obviously, that's not enough
Not we've been banned by China for the 37th time and this time they really mean it
That's not enough right not Trump just call this drug dealers
Not enough like we've been called drug dealers before by more serious people
It's not enough for even Facebook or JPMorgan to say hey we can do cryptocurrency too now you get
Not enough the only way Bitcoin fails is from the inside
it has to fail because of a
Critical vulnerability that cannot be fixed or the people don't want to fix it
has to fail because of a failure of community as
the fail because of failure a trust or culture and that's really difficult to do in a technology that has
so many participants
who have so many different motivations different cultures different languages different operating systems different software platforms all
collaborating around one core basic set of ideas
They have to all be disappointed for different reasons
Simultaneously very difficult to happen and for the same reason that if you want to find to the next etherium first
Etherium has to fail at being if the current etherium in order for something else to pop up now
This is both good news and bad news
If you're trying to push the next chip coin
It's bad news because I'm sorry to tell you you don't have the next Bitcoin or the next aetherium in
Fact many of the ideas out. There are either too early to have any success or not
differentiated enough
From the current marketplace you can have the best idea and the best team in the world and if it's not your time yet
You fail completely, right?
Some people say, you know, but look a facebook or myspace or Google Google was the 21st search engine
They waited until the first twenty failed
Right. How many here used AltaVista?
Yeah, how many here still use AltaVista?
Now remember Microsoft came along and said we're the next Google we even have a fun name it's like Bing
How many of you use Bing unless you're on a new computer where you can't install an alternative
Right
It's very difficult to unseat a technology that has already fully occupied a space
now the good news is at
the same time that if one of these technologies fails and
Vacates that environment we now know that it's a rich environment
That can support a very very successful
System which means there will be a whole line of candidates waiting to be the next X
Which should be really bad news?
to all of the governments and regulators and large
Corporations that are hoping so hard after ten years of evidence that it's just not happening that this here
Bitcoin will surely fail this year
Bitcoin will get shut down
They've been hoping they mean telling themselves. Don't worry. There's no way governments would allow this
There's no good way. This will be successful and
After ten years of being wrong
They're still holding on to hope that this thing will fail on its own because they have no fucking clue how to compete with it
Well, here's the bad news for them the moment it fails
Every single competitor that has a slightly better solution and
specifically the ones that fix the thing that caused it to fail in the first place will flood that environment and
Bootstrap something new and if they're really smart if they're really smart
They're going to call it Bitcoin
because that's the best branding you can do and
So it never dies
because
Who occupies the space and has the name keeps changing?
But you still occupy the same space and maybe even you still
Occupy the same name and that's why the next bitcoin is
Bitcoin, thank you
You